"Animal Protein vs. Plant-Based Protein"
In 2019, Dr. David Katz
and colleagues—
including one of my favorite
researchers, David Jenkins—
published a public health
case for modernizing
the definition of protein quality.
The prevailing definition seems to
have more to do with biochemistry
than the net effects on human health.
The popular concept that protein
is good, and the more the better,
coupled with a protein quality
definition that favors animal protein,
fosters the impression that eating
more meat, eggs, and dairy
is desirable and preferable,
but this is directly opposed
to nutrition guidelines that are
instead trying to push more plants.
Although protein malnutrition is still
prevalent in many areas of the world,
it is exceedingly rare
in the industrialized world,
where the most formidable
public health threat
is not something like kwashiorkor—
protein/calorie malnutrition—
but from chronic diseases.
In 2016, a landmark study
was published out of Harvard,
involving more than 100,000 people,
that found that replacing animal protein
with plant protein was associated
with lower risk of dying prematurely.
The worst seemed to be
processed meat like bacon,
as well as egg protein,
the egg whites,
but swapping in even just 3% plant
protein for any of the animal proteins—
processed meat, unprocessed meat,
chicken, fish, eggs, or dairy—
was associated with a
significantly lower risk
of arguably the most important
endpoint of all: death.
Yeah, but how do we
know it's the protein?
The researchers adjusted for factors
such as saturated fat intake,
which suggested it wasn't
just the animal fat.
Okay, but how does your body
even know the difference
between protein from a plant
and protein from an animal?
Isn't protein, protein?
No. Unlike animal protein,
plant protein is generally low
in branched-chain
amino acids, for example,
and decreased consumption
of branched-chain amino acids
improves metabolic health.
It could be the IGF-1,
a cancer-promoting growth
hormone that is boosted
by so-called high-quality
animal protein intake, though.
We suspect the IGF-1
connection is cause and effect,
since people who are born
to have higher IGF-1 levels
regardless of what they eat
do appear to suffer
higher rates of killers like
type 2 diabetes and heart disease.
Or it could be something the
Harvard researchers didn't control for
such as toxic pollutants like
as dioxins and PBCs,
since they tend to accumulate
up the food chain in cattle,
pigs, chickens, and fish,
and therefore end up on our plates.
So plant-based protein also
stands as an important step
to lower the body burden
of harmful pollutants.
If you don't think 100,000
people are enough,
how about 400,000 people?
The NIH-AARP study is the largest
diet cohort study in history.
And again, simply swapping
3% of calories from various
animal protein sources
with plant protein
was associated with 10%
decreased overall mortality,
and you get even twice that benefit
if you get rid of eggs, too.
That's not a surprise, since
egg consumption is associated
with a higher risk of developing
cardiovascular disease.
Put all the studies together on
dietary protein intake and mortality,
and people who eat more protein
tend to live shorter lives,
but this is mainly driven by the
harmful association of animal protein.
Plant protein intake is inversely
associated with mortality,
meaning those who eat more plant
protein tend to live longer lives.
More animal protein
may mean more mortality,
whereas more plant protein
is correlated with less mortality.
So the best of both worlds
would be to increase
the intake of plant protein
in place of animal protein.
In other words, as another
2020 meta-analysis concluded,
"Persons should be encouraged to
increase their plant protein intake
to potentially decrease
their risk of death."